<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2031 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2031.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4071 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4071.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4371 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4371.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-iasa2-struct SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-iasa2-struct.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-rationale SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-iasa2-trust-rationale.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-update SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-iasa2-trust-update.xml">
<!ENTITY BCP78 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.BCP.78.xml">

]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="informational" docName="draft-ietf-iasa2-rfc2031bis" ipr="trust200902" replaces="2031">

<front>

<title abbrev="The Updated IETF-ISOC Relationship">
	The Updated IETF-ISOC Relationship
</title>
	
	<author fullname="Gonzalo Camarillo" initials="G." surname="Camarillo">
		<organization>Ericsson</organization>
	    	<address>
		<email>Gonzalo.Camarillo@ericsson.com</email>
		</address>
	</author>
    
	<author fullname="Jason Livingood" initials="J." surname="Livingood">
		<organization>Comcast</organization>
		<address>
		<email>jason_livingood@comcast.com</email>
		</address>
	  </author>
    
<date month="October" year="2018" />

<area>General</area>

<workgroup>IETF Administrative Support Activity 2</workgroup>

<abstract>
	<t>This document summarises the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) - Internet Society (ISOC) 
		relationship, following a major revision to the structure of the IETF Administrative Support 
		Activity (IASA) in 2018. The IASA was revised under a new "IASA 2.0" structure by 
		the IASA2 Working Group, which changed the IETF's administrative, legal, and financial structure. As 
		a result, it also changed the relationship between the IETF and ISOC and necessitated a 
		revision of RFC 2031.
	</t>
      
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction and History">
	
	<t>The Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) is the body that is responsible for the development 
		and maintenance of the Internet Standards. The IETF is primarily a volunteer organization. 
		The driving force is dedicated, high quality engineers from all over the world. In a structure 
		of working groups, these engineers exchange ideas and experience, and through discussion and 
		collaboration (both by electronic and face-to-face) they strive to achieve rough consensus and 
		implement the standards through running code.</t>
	
	<t>The growth of the Internet over several decades has also led to a growth of the IETF. More people, 
		organizations, and companies rely on Internet Standards with every new day. Non-technical issues, 
		such as legal, administrative, and financial issues have long been an undesirable but unavoidable 
		part of the IETF. To address these issues the IETF initially established the Poised95 Working Group 
		in 1995 to structure and document the IETF processes in such a way as to maximize the flexibility 
		and freedom of the engineers in the IETF so that they can work in the way the IETF has always 
		been most successful, and to honour the IETF credo: "Rough consensus and running code".</t>
	
	<t>The Poised95 Working Group concluded that the Internet Society (ISOC), which was formed in 1992, was 
		the best organization to handle all of these legal, administrative, and financial tasks on behalf 
		of and in close cooperation with the IETF. This led to the creation of a series of documents, such as 
		The IETF Standards Process, The IETF organizational structure, The IETF charter, The IETF Nominating 
		Committee (NomCom) procedures, The Appeals procedures, and so on. 
		[EDITOR ACTION: INFORMATIVE REFERENCES NEEDED FOR EACH]</t>
	
	<t>As time passed and operational experience accumulated, additional structure was necessary. As a result, 
		documents were written in order to more fully define what was called the Internet Administrative 
		Support Activity (IASA) in 2005. The key documents supporting the initial definition of the IASA 
		were <xref target="RFC4071"/> and <xref target="RFC4371"/>.</t>

 	<t>In 2018, the IASA was revised under a new "IASA 2.0" structure by the IASA2 Working Group. This made 
		signifincant revisions to the IETF's administrative, legal, and financial structure. One critical 
		outcome was that the IETF formed the IETF Administration Limited Liability Company (IETF LLC), 
		in close cooperation with ISOC.</t>
	
	<t>As a result, the IASA 2.0 structure <xref target="I-D.ietf-iasa2-struct"/> and formation of the IETF 
		LLC have changed the relationship between the IETF and ISOC. This document summarises the 
		current state of the IETF - ISOC relationship at a high level and replaces <xref target="FRC2031"/>.</t>
	
</section>
    	
<section title="Main Division of Responsibilities Between IETF and ISOC">
      
      <t>The IETF remains responsible for the development and quality of the
   Internet Standards. The Internet Society will aid the IETF by facilitating legal
   and organizational issues as described below. Apart from the roles
   described below, the IETF and ISOC acknowledge that the ISOC has no
   influence whatsoever on the Internet Standards process, the Internet
	      Standards or their technical content.</t>

   <t>All subgroups in the IETF and ISOC that have an official role in the
   standards process should be either:
	   <list style="none">
   		<t>- open to anyone (like IETF Working Groups); or
		<t>- have a well documented restricted membership in which the voting members are elected 
	   or nominated through an open process. [EDITOR'S NOTE: Is "restricted" necessary here?]</t>
	   </list></t>

  <t> The latter means that, within the IETF, the Internet Architecture Board (IAB) 
	  and the Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG) need to be
   formed through a nomination process that is acceptable to the IETF
   community and that gives all IETF participants an equal chance to be a
   candidate for a position in either of these bodies. 
	  
	  [EDITOR'S NOTE: This next sentence is from the original RFC but not sure
	  with new ISOC bylaws this is even the case any longer. Suggest that 
	  this be revised as needed.]
	  
	  For the Internet Society, this
   means that the Board of Trustees should be elected by ISOC's
   individual membership, where all individual members have an equal
   vote and all individual members have an equal opportunity to stand as
	  a candidate for a position on the Board of Trustees.</t>
	    
   <t>The Internet Society will, like the IETF, use public discussion, 
	   community consultation, and consensus building
   processes when it wants to develop new policies or procedures that
   may influence the role of ISOC in the Internet or the Internet
   Technical work. 
	   
	  [EDITOR'S NOTE: This next sentence is from the original RFC but not it 
	   is correct to say that ISOC will consult on technical issues 
	   via IETF I-Ds. I do not recall that on my time on the ISOC Board. 
	   Usually it was in consultation with the IESG and IAB.]
	   
	   
	   The Internet Society will always put work related to Internet
   standards, Internet technical issues, or Internet operations up for
   discussion in the IETF through the IETF Internet-drafts publication
   process.</t>

    </section>
	  
<section anchor="standards" title="ISOC's Role in the IETF Standards Process">

[EDITOR'S NOTE: Is the 3rd bullet still correct?]
	
	<t>ISOC will assist the standards process by:</t>
		<t><list style="none">
		<t>- appointing the IETF NomCom chair</t>
		<t>- approving IAB candidates that were put forward by the IETF NomCom</t>
     		<t>- reviewing and approving the documents that describe the standards 
			process</t>
     		<t>- acting as the last resort in the appeals process</t>
		</list></t>

</section>
	
<section title="Philosophical Relationship with ISOC">

	<t>TBD - perhaps touch on the alignment of ideology of the 2 orgs and their shared history</t>

</section>
	
<section title="Legal Relationship with ISOC">

	<t>The IETF LLC was organized as a “disregarded entity” of ISOC. This means it operates 
	      as a branch or division of ISOC for tax purposes. ISOC operates as a U.S. 501(c)(3) 
	      not-for-profit organization, and was founded to support and promote the development 
	      of the Internet as a global technical infrastructure, a resource to enrich 
	      people’s lives, and a force for good in society. Governing the relationship 
	      between the IETF LLC and ISOC is an Operating Agreement, which was agreed to in 2018. 
	      [REFERENCE NEEDED HERE?]</t>
	
	<t>As a result of the creation of the IETF LLC, the IETF now has its own legal umbrella. This 
		IETF LLC structure now covers the IETF standards and IETF standards process, all IETF 
		officers (IAB, IESG, Nomcom and WG chairs), IETF employees and contractors, the RFC 
		series and RFC editor, etc.</t>
	
	<t>The IETF Trust, documented in <xref="BCP78"/>, and updated in <xref="I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-rationale"/> and 
		<xref="I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-update"/>, provides legal protection for the RFC series 
		of documents and other aspects of the IETF. This include things such as protection for trademarks, 
		copyrights, and intellectual property rights. As part of the IETF Trust arrangement, IETF standards 
		documents can be freely downloaded, copied, and distributed without financial or other 
		distribution restrictions, though all rights to change these documents lie with the IETF. 
		The IETF Trust also provides legal protection in case of disputes over intellectual property 
		rights and other rights.</t>

</section>

<section title="Financial and Administrative Relationship with ISOC">

	<t>The IETF LLC was organized as a “disregarded entity” of Internet Society. This means it operates 
	      as a branch or division of ISOC for tax purposes. ISOC operates as a U.S. 501(c)(3) 
	      not-for-profit organization, and was founded to support and promote the development 
	      of the Internet as a global technical infrastructure, a resource to enrich 
	      people’s lives, and a force for good in society.</t>
	
	<t>Under the terms of the ISOC - IETF LLC Operating Agreement, ISOC has agreed to provide some funding 
		support for the IETF. But the IETF LLC will be responsible for creating and managing an annual 
		operating budget for the IETF, as well as for fundraising, maintaining a bank account, managing 
		the IETF Endowment, and so on.</t>

	<t>The IETF is solely responsible for its administration under the new IASA 2.0 structure and via 
		the IETF LLC, IETF Trust, IAB, IESG, IETF working groups, and other IETF processes. A further 
	exploration of this can be found in Section 4 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-iasa2-struct"/>. </t>

</section>	



<section title="Security Considerations">

	<t>This document introduces no new security considerations.</t>
	<t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section upon publication.]</t>

</section>
	
<section title="Privacy Considerations">

	<t>This document introduces no new privacy considerations.</t>
	<t>[RFC Editor: Please remove this section upon publication,]</t>

</section>
	  
<section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
	
	<t>The authors would like to thank Erik Huizer for his contribution as the 
		author of <xref target="RFC2031"/>, which this document replaces.</t>
	
</section>

<section anchor="changes" title="Changes from Previous Versions">
	<t>RFC Editor: Please remove this section upon publication.</t>
	<t>-00: Initial version published</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">
	
</references>
    
<references title="Informative References">
	
	&BCP78;
	&RFC2031;
	&RFC4071;
	&RFC4371;
	&I-D.ietf-iasa2-struct;
	&I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-rationale;
	
</references>

</back>
	
</rfc>
