<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2026 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2028 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2028.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2031 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2031.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2282 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2282.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2850 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2850.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3677 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3677.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4033 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4071 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4071.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4371 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4371.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5378 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5378.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6756 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6756.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7437 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7437.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8200 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8200.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-iasa2-rfc4071bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-iasa2-rfc4071bis.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-rationale SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-rationale.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-update SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-update.xml">


]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-iasa2-rfc2031bis-04" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="2031">

<front>

<title abbrev="The IETF-ISOC Relationship">
	The IETF-ISOC Relationship
</title>
	
	<author fullname="Gonzalo Camarillo" initials="G." surname="Camarillo">
		<organization>Ericsson</organization>
	    	<address>
		<email>Gonzalo.Camarillo@ericsson.com</email>
		</address>
	</author>
    
	<author fullname="Jason Livingood" initials="J." surname="Livingood">
		<organization>Comcast</organization>
		<address>
		<email>jason_livingood@comcast.com</email>
		</address>
	  </author>
    
<date month="February" year="2019" />

<area>General</area>

<workgroup>IETF Administrative Support Activity 2</workgroup>

<abstract>
  <t>
This document summarises the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) -
Internet Society (ISOC) relationship, following a major revision to
the structure of the IETF Administrative Support Activity (IASA) in
2018. The IASA was revised under a new "IASA 2.0" structure by the
IASA2 Working Group, which changed the IETF's administrative, legal,
and financial structure. As a result, it also changed the relationship
between the IETF and ISOC, which made it necessary to revise RFC 2031.
  </t>

</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction and History">
  	
  <t>
The Internet Society provides a corporate home for the administrative
entity that supports the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF), the
Internet Architecture Board (IAB), and the Internet Research Task
Force (IRTF), and supports the work of these groups through a variety
of programs.
  </t>

  <t>
The Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) is the body that is
responsible for the development and maintenance of the Internet
Standards. The IETF is primarily a volunteer organization. Its driving
force is a group of dedicated high-quality engineers from all over the
world. In a structure of working groups, these engineers exchange
ideas and experience, and through discussion and collaboration (both
electronically and face-to-face) they strive to achieve rough
consensus and implement the standards through running code.
  </t>
	
  <t>
The growth of the Internet over several decades also led to the
growth of the IETF. More and more people, organizations, and companies
rely on Internet Standards. Non-technical issues, such as legal,
administrative, and financial issues had long been an undesirable but
unavoidable part of the IETF. To address these issues in 1995 the IETF
established the Poised95 Working Group. Its goal was to structure and
document the IETF processes in order to maximize the flexibility and
freedom of IETF engineers so that they could work in the way the IETF
had always been most successful and to honour the IETF credo: "Rough
consensus and running code".
  </t>
	
  <t>
The Poised95 Working Group concluded that the Internet Society (ISOC),
which was formed in 1992, was the best organization to handle all of
these legal, administrative, and financial tasks on behalf of and in
close cooperation with the IETF. This led to documenting things such
as the IETF standards process <xref target="RFC2026"/>, the IETF
organizational structure <xref target="RFC2028"/>, the IETF Nominating
Committee (NomCom) procedures <xref target="RFC2282"/>, and the IETF-ISOC
relationship <xref target="RFC2031"/>.
  </t>
	
  <t>
As time passed and operational experience accumulated, additional
structure was necessary. As a result, the Internet Administrative
Support Activity (IASA) was defined in 2005 and documented in <xref
target="RFC4071"/> and <xref target="RFC4371"/>.
  </t>

  <t>
In 2018, the IASA was revised under a new "IASA 2.0" structure by the
IASA2 Working Group, which made significant revisions to the IETF's
administrative, legal, and financial structure. One critical outcome
was the formation, in close cooperation between the IETF and
ISOC, of the IETF Administration Limited Liability Company (IETF LLC)
as a subsidiary of ISOC.
  </t>
	
  <t>
As a result of the the IASA 2.0 structure <xref
target="I-D.ietf-iasa2-rfc4071bis"/> and formation of the IETF LLC, the
relationship between the IETF and ISOC has changed. This document
summarises the current state of the IETF - ISOC relationship at a high
level and replaces <xref target="RFC2031"/>.
  </t>
	
</section>

	
<section title="Philosophical Relationship with ISOC">

  <t>
ISOC and the IETF have historically been philosophically
aligned. ISOC's connection with the IETF community has always played
an important role in its policy work. ISOC has always been an advocate
for multistakeholder processes, which include the technical
community. Open standards are an explicit part of one of the focus
areas in ISOC's mission: Advancing the development and application of
Internet infrastructure, technologies, and open standards.
   </t>

</section>

    	
<section title="Main Division of Responsibilities between IETF and ISOC">
      
  <t>
The IETF remains responsible for the development and quality of the
Internet Standards. Apart from the roles described below, the IETF and
ISOC acknowledge that ISOC has no influence whatsoever on the
technical content of Internet Standards.
  </t>

    </section>

<section anchor="standards" title="ISOC's Role in the IETF Standards Process">

  <t>
ISOC plays a small role in the IETF standards process. In particular,
ISOC assists the standards process by appointing the IETF NomCom chair
and by confirming IAB candidates who are put forward by the IETF
NomCom, as described in <xref target="RFC7437"/>, and by acting as the
last resort in the appeals process, as described in <xref
target="RFC2026"/>.
  </t>
	
  <t>
ISOC maintains liaison relationships and memberships in other
Standards Development Organizations (SDOs) and related organizations,
which directly benefits the IETF. For example, ISOC is a Sector Member
of the ITU-T. As a result, ISOC delegates are afforded the same rights
as other ITU-T Sector Members <xref target="RFC6756"/>.
  </t>

  <t>
ISOC also supports the IETF standards process more indirectly (e.g.,
by promoting it in relevant communities) through several
programmes. For example, ISOC's Policymakers Programme to the IETF
(usually referred to simply as ISOC's policy fellows programme) gives
policy experts an opportunity to interact directly with the IETF
technical community. ISOC also performs technical work using the
standards developed in the IETF as its basis. An example of that is
ISOC's Deploy360 program, which helps encourage and support the
deployment of critical new IETF standards like DNSSEC  <xref
target="RFC4033"/> and IPv6  <xref
target="RFC8200"/>.
  </t>
	
  <t>
Otherwise, the involvement of ISOC's employees in the IETF standards
process (e.g., as document editors or in leadership positions) is as
individual contributors rather than on institutional grounds.
  </t>
  
</section>

<section title="The IETF's Role in ISOC">

  <t>
The IETF plays a role in the governance of ISOC. Per ISOC's by-laws,
the IETF appoints a set of trustees to the ISOC Board. The process by
which the IETF makes those appointments is defined in <xref
target="RFC3677"/>.
  </t>

  <t>
The charter of the IAB (Internet Architecture Board) <xref
target="RFC2850"/> states that "the IAB acts as a source of advice and
guidance to the Board of Trustees and Officers of the Internet Society
concerning technical, architectural, procedural, and (where
appropriate) policy matters pertaining to the Internet and its
enabling technologies". This connection between the IAB and ISOC
ensures that ISOC's proposals in the policy area are based on a sound
understanding of the relevant technologies and architectures. ISOC's
strong connection to the Internet technical community has always been
one of its main strengths.
  </t>

</section>


<section title="Legal Relationship with ISOC">

  <t>
The IETF LLC was created as a subsidiary of ISOC. Specifically, the
IETF LLC is a single-member Limited Liability Company created in
Delaware (USA) in August 2018.  The member (i.e., its legal owner) is
ISOC. The IETF LLC is managed separately, makes a budget, can sign
contracts, can pay and receive money, can sue and be sued, and has a
board. ISOC operates as a U.S. 501(c)(3) not-for-profit organization,
and was founded to support and promote the development of the Internet
as a global technical infrastructure, a resource to enrich people's
lives, and a force for good in society. The Limited Liability Company
Agreement of IETF Administration LLC, dated August 27 2018, is the
Operating Agreement <xref target="OpAgreement"/> that governs the
relationship between the IETF LLC and ISOC (while this document is
intended as a summary of the agreement, please note that only the
agreement is authoritative).
  </t>
	
  <t>
The IETF LLC provides the IETF with a separate legal existence. The
IETF LLC structure now covers (from a legal perspective) the IETF
standards and IETF standards process, all IETF officers (IAB, IESG,
Nomcom, and WG chairs), IETF employees and contractors, the RFC series
and RFC editor, and all of the IETF's other business operations.
  </t>
	
<t>
For tax purposes, the IETF LLC is considered a part of ISOC, known
as a "disregarded entity".  This means that the IETF LLC shares ISOC's
tax exempt status as a not-for-profit charity, and contributions to
the LLC are tax deductible under U.S. law as they would be if they
were made to ISOC.
</t>
	
  <t>
The IETF Trust, documented in <xref target="RFC5378"/>, and updated in
<xref target="I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-rationale"/> and <xref
target="I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-update"/>, provides legal protection for
the RFC series of documents and other aspects of the IETF. This
includes things such as protection for trademarks, copyrights, and
intellectual property rights. As part of the IETF Trust arrangement,
IETF standards documents can be freely downloaded, copied, and
distributed without financial or other distribution restrictions,
though all rights to change these documents lie with the IETF.  The
IETF Trust also provides legal protection in case of disputes over
intellectual property rights and other rights. The creation of the
IETF LLC has changed the way that the IETF Trust's trustees are
selected but did not change the purpose or operation of the Trust. One
of the IETF Trust's trustees is appointed by the ISOC's board of
trustees.
  </t>

</section>

<section title="Financial and Administrative Relationship with ISOC">
	
  <t>
Under the terms of the Operating Agreement <xref
target="OpAgreement"/> between ISOC and the IETF, ISOC has agreed to
provide some funding support for the IETF (ISOC has historically
provided the IETF with significant financial support).  In particular,
among other things, the IETF LLC will be responsible for creating and
managing an annual operating budget for the IETF; for negotiating,
signing, and overseeing contracts; for fund raising; for maintaining a
bank account; and for liability insurance. The IETF LLC is managed by
a board of directors, one of whom is appointed by the ISOC's board of
trustees. The intention is that ISOC and the IETF LLC operate at arms
length.
  </t>  
	
  <t>	
The IETF LCC establishes contracts with third parties to provide
different types of services to the IETF. Note that it is possible that
some of those services are provided by ISOC or involve ISOC staff.
  </t>	
  
  <t>
Under the new IASA 2.0 structure, the IETF is solely responsible for
its administration via the IETF LLC, IETF Trust, IAB, IESG, IETF
working groups, and other IETF processes. A further exploration of
this can be found in Section 4 of <xref
target="I-D.ietf-iasa2-rfc4071bis"/>.
  </t>

</section>	

<section title="IANA Considerations">

	<t>This document introduces no new IANA considerations.</t>

</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">

	<t>This document introduces no new security considerations.</t>

</section>
	
<section title="Privacy Considerations">

	<t>This document introduces no new privacy considerations.</t>

</section>
	  
<section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
	
  <t>
The authors would like to thank Erik Huizer for his contribution as
the author of <xref target="RFC2031"/>, which this document
replaces.
  </t>
	
</section>

<section anchor="changes" title="Changes from Previous Versions">
	<t>RFC Editor: Please remove this section upon publication.</t>
	<t>-00: Initial version published</t>
	<t>-01: Several key updates to prepare WGLC based on WG feedback</t>
	<t>-02: Fixed nits identified by Brian Carpenter on 12-21-2018, and text on the tax status from John Levine.</t>
	<t>-03: As we entered IESG review, added a short description of what ISOC does (in relation to the IETF) 
		that can be used in external material by both the IETF and ISOC.</t>
	<t>-04: Clarification adding text to Section 6 on legal issue.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

<!--
  <references title="Normative References">
	
  </references>
-->

<references title="Informative References">

        &RFC2026;
    	&RFC2028;
    	&RFC2031;
   	&RFC2282;
   	&RFC2850;	
	&RFC3677;
	&RFC4033;
	&RFC4071;
	&RFC4371;
	&RFC5378;	
	&RFC6756;
	&RFC7437;
	&RFC8200;		
	&I-D.ietf-iasa2-rfc4071bis;
	&I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-rationale;
        &I-D.ietf-iasa2-trust-update;


    <reference anchor='OpAgreement'>
       <front> 
         <title abbrev='Operating Agreement'>Limited Liability Company
Agreement of IETF Administration LLC</title>
<author />
         <date month='August' year='2018' /> 
       </front>
    </reference>

    
</references>

</back>
	
</rfc>
